[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen
i have with me today
two mats
matt butcher and
matt farina
matt butcher is a ceo at fermion
technologies he is a founding member of
many open source projects including helm
matt farina is a distinguished engineer
at suse and the co-chair of kubernetes
sig apps
and his maintainer on helm
along with josh dalitsky who is not here
today they are the authors of the book
learning helm
managing apps on kubernetes and we will
be talking about helm
before we get started i want to refer
listeners to episode 446 about
kubernetes and 489 on package management
matt and matt
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks for having us thanks for having
us this is our first ever episode with
two maps on the same
episode very distinguished before we get
started would either you like to say
anything about your background that i
didn't cover all right yeah i've been
working in open source for a long time
now you know most recently i worked for
a startup called deus who got into the
container ecosystem very early i think
we were using kubernetes when it was
about 1.0 1.1
some of the members on my team wrote
things like the docker volume system and
or contributed to the docker volume
system
and we were kind of building a platform
as a service at the time
we discovered kubernetes and it was like
a light bulb went on and we were we just
sort of instantly fell in love and that
really got us sort of wholeheartedly
invested in kubernetes helm came out of
that a number of other tools came out of
that the illustrated children guides to
kubernetes came out of that and we never
looked back went on from there became
part of microsoft spent years developing
there and then most recently i left
microsoft with some of my my friends and
we started a company called fermion
technologies for the listeners that was
matt butcher
matt farina would you like to add
anything
yeah certainly thanks butcher for going
first it gave me some time to think
about it well you just off the top of
your head had to rattle something off
so i'm matt farina you'll probably hear
me referred to as farina on here
so i came to a different route to all
this so i'm a distinguished engineer at
susa and more recently i'm on the
technical oversight committee rather
than being on kubernetes sig apps or
architecture anymore because that's a
lot of work to have all those and so
that's where i'm at these days
and i came to helm through a different
route at the time i was co-chair of
kubernetes sega apps and helm had become
a sub-project as part of kubernetes
before it had rolled off to be a full
cloud native computing foundation
project
i got pulled in to just start helping
working on the charts and that's the
packages we'll talk more about and just
getting involved in how they work and
automation around them and tooling and i
eventually became a full uh hell
maintainer through that process of
contributing and matt and i have a long
history of collaborating on things so it
was very easy for me to get into the
flow of working with him in fact i think
we've known each other since 2009 we
were doing drupal websites together back
then yeah yes we were something like
2009 and we worked together at two
companies this is this book was our
third book working on together you've
wrote me into a lot of things
and for the listeners that was matt
farina
today we will be talking about helm
a package manager for kubernetes
before we get into the main part of the
discussion i'd like to do a brief review
of kubernetes and a brief review of
package management
one of you pick each one of those and
give a thumbnail you want to take
kubernetes i'll take package management
sure i'll take kubernetes so kubernetes
is a you know it's billed as a container
orchestration system and it can be more
generally used as an orchestration
system in general to orchestrate other
things as well but the way i like to
think about it is it's kind of like a
cluster-wide operating system and it can
scale from one machine up to many and in
this case your workloads are the
different containers that you're running
and they can be scheduled across the
hardware i like to think about it sort
of like you've got hot swappable
hardware when you have a cluster where
if something fails it gets rescheduled
elsewhere you can easily add more to it
but it's sort of a platform for running
things primarily containers whether
you're talking about just and doing it
in a declarative way where you tell the
system here's what you want to run and
then it figures out how to run that as
best it can doing things like bin
packing on servers scheduling things
close to each other and doing that for
you you think that's a pretty good
explanation matt yeah yeah in fact you
know you know the whole kubernetes as an
operating system thing is really my
favorite way to describe kubernetes and
that was sort of one of the early aha
moments that led us to helm because one
of the core features of pretty much all
popular operating systems is they have
some sort of package management
and you know sort of roughly conceived
right package management is just a
system that allows you the user of a
system of an operating system or of a
programming language or something a
pattern and a repository full of things
that you can fetch and install locally
right so you'll have a command to
grab something and install it locally
you'll have a command to package up
something locally and push it back up
into the repository and then a whole
bunch of auxiliary and helper commands
and when we first started working in
kubernetes at deus we were building a
pas application that was supposed to sit
on top of kubernetes things were going
great as far as building this path
system when platform as a service we
were you know solving a lot of problems
kubernetes was doing great things for us
but then when it came to installing
we were like you know asking the user to
walk through the installer to walk
through a whole bunch of individual
steps to get each little piece and part
installed one at a time and and
configured and you know as as the story
goes right we had a all company meeting
the purpose of the meeting was to
announce to the entire company that we
were going to pivot from you know
multi-platform to just doing kubernetes
and part of that meeting was a hackathon
project my team in the hackathon project
went wouldn't it be cool if we solved
this particular problem if we tried to
figure out how to do package management
for kubernetes
so that others as they come to
kubernetes will be able to easily get
started easily install those first few
bits and then easily start building up
their own packages that
house the configuration for their own
applications and that was really where
helm came from you got a little bit into
this matt butcher in your last
comment what does a developer experience
look like on kubernetes without helm and
how does it change when you adopt helm
without helm kubernetes really is
configured via a whole bunch of yaml
files
you'll have to write a yaml file a file
in the ml format that describes each
object that you want to put into the
kubernetes cluster
some of these objects will be things
like deployments which describe to
kubernetes what the application is how
it should be deployed how it should be
upgraded other things will be more on
the configuration side like config maps
or secrets which will hold just you know
essentially configuration data set
settings files preference files things
like that and then you'll have other
things like network attached storage and
information about how services come up
so as you're as you're listening to the
litany of things i'm describing i want
you to imagine writing about a 200 line
to 500 line yaml file to describe each
and every one of these things so to
install your typical application you're
talking about writing you know six to
eight hundred lines of yaml just to get
going right and then it grows from there
and then each different kubernetes
cluster with each different kind of
ingress controller or whatever its
nuances and details are would require
different variations of that same yaml
file
that that works well when you have a
very small number of things and a very
well-known set of features that you need
to support but if you're trying to
install somebody else's application it
is no fun to attempt to generate all
those things or if you're responsible
for deploying the same application to
of and dozens of different kubernetes
clusters it's no fun to do that so helm
really provided a way to
package up these yaml files together but
also to parameterize them and templatize
them and make it possible for someone to
say hey here's my deployment but if i'm
running on an aws cluster with these
constraints and these configurations
then tweak things over here according to
this template but if we're running in
say azure then tweak these other things
over here and run it this way and if
we're running on-prem here's a third
different version right so in a sense
it's a it's a packaging up of those yaml
files but also in such a way that the
operator at the time they install
something into the cluster has the
ability to provide specific
configuration values and turn on and off
different dials and switches to make it
install just right into their cluster if
i understood
the difficulty of installing a complex
system on kubernetes is there could be
10 or 20 different kubernetes objects
and not only the individual objects need
to be
configured correctly but also the
associations between them and that
one thing needs to point to a field in
another thing
helm is a way of encapsulating all the
object and getting the associations
between them correct so you can install
correctly
is that more or less right
sort of so so this is matt frane i'm
gonna jump in here
the way i like to look at it is say i'm
going to go install something on linux
right like postgres
and
you've got to know where if you do it by
hand where to put configuration files
where to put binaries and how to wire it
all up together you need to know how to
do that in kubernetes if you're going to
go install something say wordpress it's
a popular thing you're going to have a
bunch of different resource types
secrets deployments stateful sets maybe
an ingress controller
you might have volume claims things like
this and you've got to wire all of those
things up to go together and so
everybody who does it by hand has to
know how all those manifests work in
kubernetes how to wire them together and
they have to know
how the
how the business logic of the app works
in order to do that
and just like if i were going to go
install something like postgres on linux
where i could do you know zipper install
or app install postgres and just get it
without having to know this that's what
you get with helm i could do helm
install
and give it some information and say you
know do you do wordpress and it can go
install that with default values just
like there or just like you can with
other package managers you can override
those defaults and so it makes that user
experience a lot simpler through using
templates and parameterization and
trying to use intelligent defaults which
the package author gets to choose you
mentioned wordpress
give some other examples of popular
packages that you can install with helm
well i guess some of the other popular
packages you could do most of the
databases right postgres maria mysql
redis so you can get into some of
those database systems most of the
things that you can think about is
installable services you can now find
there's a website
artifacthub.io which is another cncf
project that lists lots of these things
and so you can find stuff over there
butcher do you have any other ideas of
other things other things are escaping
my mind right now yeah i think you kind
of see helm charts break down into three
big categories right i think there are
the infrastructure layer categories
things that augment kubernetes itself
service meshes
things that require custom resource
definitions you'll see a number of those
and then the second one is really sort
of that that data plane or the the
underpinnings that you would need to
write in application databases key value
storage nosql things like that you tend
to see a good a good grouping of those
in fact last i checked i think almost
every major database nosql database and
key value storage had a helm chart
somewhere and then the last one is those
end user style applications where
someone would want to install it and
have it running and be able to
immediately hit the front end of the web
interface and start doing whatever they
want to do content management systems
like wordpress are a good example and
issue trackers the you know those kinds
of things that we all have we all have
toyed around with running these
applications locally at one point or
another in the past and now you want to
have sort of a productionized version
running in your cluster so those i think
are really the three categories we tend
to see best represented in places like
artifact hub matt butcher you gave a
short description of how helm came into
being i understand it has quite a long
history now
we're up to helm three
what are the major evolutions that have
occurred in going from zero to three
so helm one who was originally which we
now call helm classic was originally
conceived of just as sort of like a yaml
file uploader it didn't have originally
did not have template support didn't
have a lot of management features for
what to do after you'd installed
something you could kind of think of it
as a tarball full of yaml files and a
tool that would unturn it and push all
of those yaml files up into the cluster
again you know keeping in mind use case
number one for us we were trying to
figure out a way to install deus
workflow our platform as a service and
that was a good that was a good first
step there was actually a lot of
controversy at the time about whether
template fire whether yaml files should
be templatized or parameterized there
were a lot of people who felt very
strongly that they should not the
operator should have to
hand tweak the yaml files and and not
rely on some kind of settings manager or
something but as that conversation kind
of began to die down we began working on
helm2 which the template function and
template functions and the
parameterization became sort of a focal
feature set but also in helm2 we made
what i think was our biggest sort of
misstep it seemed like a logical thing
to do at the time but we moved the helm
we broke apart the helm client into two
pieces and there was helm which you ran
locally on your machine and there was
tiller which ran inside of the cluster
and helm would send the chart to tiller
and tiller would install it and then
tiller would manage state and the helm
client would just connect but over time
we hit a number of limitations with this
model and not the least of which was
security it was very very hard to lock
down tiller so that you couldn't have
people install all kinds of things sort
of willy-nilly as what was effectively
sort of like the quote unquote root user
of the kubernetes cluster
so that kicked us into our third
development cycle for helm3 which was to
move most of the logic back into the
command line client establish some
better patterns finally take a chance to
make some minor iterations on the chart
format and and that that was kind of the
big focus there
it went really well and in many many
ways helm three felt like it sort of
finally realized the the potential of
what helm could be for the ecosystem you
know we talk here and there about helm4
what will be the next big iteration and
and it's it's hard to really envision
another major set of changes like we saw
between one and two or as we saw between
two and three because effectively at
this point helm is a good solid package
manager for kubernetes you've used the
word chart a few times we should get a
definition out there sure i'll jump in
with this a chart is essentially the
package of helm right so in the
kubernetes space you'll see most or many
of the things use nautical terminology
right kubernetes it's nautical
terminology helm nautical terminology
and so in keeping with that
thread the package that helm uses is
called a chart just to keep with that
nautical terminology
many package managers have the ability
for a package to specify dependencies on
other packages the package manager will
figure out the closure of all the
dependencies and pull
everything in is that a feature of helm
so helm was not the first package
manager matt farina and i wrote we wrote
one for the go ecosystem called glide
and we worked on the dependency
resolution algorithms for quite a while
when one of the things that we sort of
derived from this was the appreciation
of the difference between an operating
systems package manager and a
programming languages package manager
and one of the desirable features on an
operating system package manager
particularly one that's
installing into a cluster is that you
really want to know up front exactly
what you're installing
and you also in addition to that may
want to install say multiple versions of
the same kind of the same thing right
mysql database for example you might
want to install multiple versions of
that in the same cluster or in some
cases we have even seen multiple
versions in the same application as
different microservices in the
application had different dependencies
and so when we began working on helm's
dependency model our our big experiment
that i think is largely turned out very
successfully has been to have the
dependency graph sort of resolved pinned
and included inside of the chart
at build time so there is zero ambiguity
about which version of which chart
you're going to get when you install
there's no negotiation of versions or
anything like that it's all
predetermined at the time at which you
package the software that said i mean
there is some dependency management that
happens early on in the development
cycle but that's not something you would
get with say cargo or npm or systems
like that where you may want to
intentionally pull whatever the latest
version of a particular package is at
build time and then you you produce a
lock file when you want to stick to just
one version or something like that
trying to think of an example
i'm guessing that if i use him to
install my sql it doesn't depend on
anything else but if i'm installing
wordpress it may want to pull in
postgres and nginx can you think of any
other examples or is my example correct
wordpress is actually a very good
example of this because you know as i
just described it sort of all the
dependencies are pulled in at build time
if you want to allow the installer to
decide between a postgres database or a
mysql database then you as the package
creator when you create the package say
okay
if you turn on this switch you get this
version of postgres configured this way
and wordpress configured to use that if
you turn on this switch this other
switch you get mysql configured this way
with wordpress pre-configured to use
that so in a way you know it pushes a
lot of the original configuration work
back to the chart developer and the
chart developer
rightfully takes their place as the
expert on the package they're producing
and says okay here's the right way to
configure postgres here's the right way
to configure my sql it's up to you which
of those two you want to choose but i
can guarantee you that when you install
them they will each work correctly
because all the versions will be pinned
to the correct number and all of the
configurations will have been things
that have been tested and so on
what is the developer interface to a
chart the primary way of developing
charts these days has been through kind
of a traditional development environment
one of the people on my team at fermion
ivan has produced the kubernetes
extension for vs code which is this
great platform that gives you
integration with kubernetes it gives you
helm chart development tools and
provides you a lot of you know auto
complete style features template
reference kinds of features that help
you build charts very rapidly matt
farina i'm i'm curious what do you use
and what other systems have you seen
well i use the vs code plugin it's hard
to say because that's kind of where my
typical workflow has been the other way
that i've seen it is people just using
the helm create command which is a
command that will stub out a chart for
you and then doing copying and pasting
from other sources a lot
but they're they tend to know their apps
business logic and kubernetes fairly
well to kind of craft a user experience
for a consumer which i think kind of
highlights in the helm community we talk
a little bit about roles and so we've
got roles like there is that chart
consumer that helm
cli user who's going to use something
then there's the person who creates a
chart and packages it up and distributes
it and we've got some of these different
roles and that end user we prioritize
higher to create a simple user
experience and so that developer who's
working on creating a chart they tend to
know kubernetes and the manifests and
the applications they're working on and
can kind of put things all together
you've mentioned
customization mechanisms namely
parameters and templates i want to
discuss each of those individually but
preface that by
what is the need
for the developer to customize a
template do the defaults work pretty
well most of the time or does it need to
be highly custom to the
settings and configurations like dns and
ip ranges and sizes and volumes on my
kubernetes cluster you know it kind of
depends on how the the chart was created
usually for things like ip ranges or
volumes you don't have to configure too
much a lot of it has to do with your
application itself for example in
kubernetes you have to deal with scaling
right quite often you don't run one
instance of something you run multiple
instances of something or you set
variation configuration parameters and
kubernetes can scale it up and down and
so you might tell it you know run a
maximum of five instances where the
chart default might be one and so
there's certain things about it that may
get into that you may have your own you
know if you're in a company you may have
pulled in the container image from
upstream the chart doesn't contain the
container image it references it because
that's how kubernetes works it goes and
pulls it and so if you're in a company
you may have pointed you know pulled
that container image down put it in your
own registry after you've scanned it or
something and you need to tell the chart
here's a different place to get that
image from and there are a number of
things like this that are around the
kubernetes that you might need to do and
customize then there are things where
people are now building in application
logic right into the chart so for
example there are wordpress charts where
i can tell you at install time here's
the name of the blog to use and that
will pass it from the chart all the way
down
into wordpress itself so when it comes
up that first time it has the right you
know site name it can have the right
configuration the right admin username
and password and so this is application
business logic that's passed all the way
down because you're able to do that
let's dive into
parameters starting with
examples of some parameters i think you
just gave some but a couple of more
examples and then how does a developer
go about setting parameters on a chart
yeah i to kind of pick up right where
matt farina left off i think one of the
most interesting
developments over the course of helm's
history has not so much been the
technology but the way that chart
developers have sort of figured out
padam's patterns for parameterizing
applications uh you know at the base
level templates will take kind of any of
the values you pass in in your
values.yml file and
these values can be specified by the
chart developer as they build out the
chart and i think originally you know we
shot for maybe five or six different
parameters without really doing much to
sort of specify boundaries around them
and things like that what we saw
was this sort of burgeoning expertise
among operators who were building these
charts who began parameterizing in a
very structured and repeatable way where
values should go in the chart and we saw
really sort of like the
professionalization of generating the
chart.yemel and the values.yaml such
that when you went from one chart to
another you could begin to see the
patterns and that i think
you know when you're getting started it
still makes sense to start out with just
trying a couple of simple name value
parameters but if you take a look at
some of the big chart repositories that
you see out on the internet what you'll
see
is you know in some cases dozens or even
hundreds of lines of possible values
that you can configure as you pass them
in and another minor change that
happened in helm3 was we allowed people
to write json schema files that would
say exactly what types of parameters
something could be so you could
essentially assist tools like vs code or
other ide style tools to say hey when's
the the parameter must be an integer or
uh must be a floating point between this
value and this value or a string or
something like that but i think really
of you know kind of the bottom line here
is we've built something that we thought
would be very flexible and people would
kind of go you know with just a few
brief things and what we've seen is
really sort of a development of an
ecosystem that that values patterns and
and that talks a lot about chart best
practices for example if i'm installing
a chart such as wordpress which is going
to go and pull in other charts such as
postgres
and maybe nginx
i would need to not only
possibly set parameters for wordpress
such as matt farina's example of the
name of the blog
but nested into the dependent packages
as well is that correct
it can be yes
and helm provides a means to do that so
say with your wordpress example and you
wanted to alter some of the replication
characteristics of your database home
when you specify those parameters in we
call them values when you specify those
in if you know you're using a particular
database and want to tweak it and it
provides parameters to tweak that you
have the ability to do that so your
whole nested chain of dependencies if
you want to go configure one of the
configurable parameters that is open to
you you know charts usually install very
simply with scene defaults and then from
there as you want to tweak things become
a little bit more of an expert on each
part of it you can go ahead and do that
we've been talking a bit about
parameters the other major customization
method is templates
what is the need for
template and why are parameters by
themselves not sufficient
yeah our first attempt was to really try
and stick to just parameterization
uh and just say hey you know here's a
value you can substitute it we even use
sort of like uh bash shell style
dollar sign
something notation but what we
discovered was that in a declarative
syntax like kubernetes there are cases
where
you want to describe where you have to
describe things using different
structures right different structural
elements not simply a string
substitution it's not simply setting the
replica account from three to five it's
saying hey if this condition obtains
then this whole section of the yaml file
needs to be different or for
configuration files here's a name here's
here's nine name value pairs you know i
need them all organized into individual
parameters plus values uh here's a list
of volumes i need to iterate twice on
them once here and once here and as we
got into those cases the declarative
format
combined with a
merely value substitution meant the
values were would be many many lines
long right it'd be dollar volumes and it
would be a 40 line value on the other
side not terribly good experience very
difficult to manage we gave up on that
very very quickly it just didn't i don't
even think no no i think helm classic
had this feature and then by helm2 we
had moved on template languages gave us
just the right level of flexibility to
say here's sort of a a minimalist
language for expressing the logical
relationships between things and for
expressing a context that needs to
surround particular values as we inject
them and
the in fact the the go template language
the syntax that we chose was really a
fairly minimal template language that
provided just kind of the features that
we felt like we really needed of course
we were wrong in asserting that and
ended up having to write a template
function library that sort of augmented
the base uh go languages but with things
that made sense right where
in one case here's another good example
of this right where mere
parameterization didn't work kubernetes
in some cases names things with capitals
and underscores all caps and underscores
and in other places all lower case with
dashes and it might be the same object
well instead of having to maintain
two versions of the same string that are
differentiated only by the
capitalization and the swapping of
underscores and dashes we could write
template functions that allowed you to
say hey in this context it needs to be
kebab case so use the dashes and
underscore in this case you know it
needs to be shouty caps so use all
capital letters and underscores and
transform the same string back and forth
ultimately then you know we have never
looked back since switching from value
substitution to templates occasionally
we've gone back and forth on whether we
chose the right template language and
i'm sure many people have opinions about
that but we chose the one that at the
time felt like the best one for the job
and have kind of stuck with it over the
years yeah i'd like to add just two
quick things here on this
the thing because i came in to helm
after the template system was in place
right that's when i could develop on it
and i was really drawn to it because i
realized that when you get to value
substitution that's one thing but a lot
of developers people who are used to
creating things are used to working with
template systems whether it's on the web
or with text it's really common to work
that out and so by doing something like
that that works across programming
languages and all these environments
it's the kind of system people are used
to
it made it easy for people to jump in
and create things and i think that was a
really useful thing for helm to add in
and make it easy for people to use
because if i go look at like packaging
managers for
operating systems i sometimes have to go
learn a new scripting language or a new
language or some a new way of doing
things and a template system is fairly
simple and what kubernetes needs in its
yaml documents
lends itself very well to templating
systems
and so i think that worked really well
in helm's behavior but i also think that
it's important to know here that it's
the chart creator who creates the
templates but the chart consumer doesn't
change them the chart consumer only
works with the parameters they pass in
and they actually don't change or work
on the templates themselves it's kind of
the way if i were working with linux and
there was a shell script inside of a
package right the package creator would
write the shell script and accept
parameters into it but you're not
necessarily going to find the package
consumer going ahead and changing that
shell script it's that same kind of
philosophy so when you run helm after
all the substitution and expanding all
the templates
what you're left with now is kubernetes
yaml files that can be deployed into
kubernetes cluster is that correct
you can run a chart to just spit out the
ml files for you but helm is takes it
one step further and says well just like
any package installer right if if i were
to apt-get install something it wouldn't
simply drop the binaries out in my local
directory would install them into place
and on occasion right it would start up
a server for me you know insert startup
scripts that kind of thing helm really
very much is inspired by that level of
package management and so
where we view the the starting point for
helm is you know creating those charts
and stuff like that but where we view
the functional endpoint for helm is it
should install something and bring it up
to running and once it's installed all
the files and all the yaml files into
the cluster and put into place all the
things that should be there that's the
point at which it says okay my work here
is done and of course then you've got
other things like upgrade and delete
which essentially you know an upgrade
will be able to diff what's there in the
cluster and what this new version of the
chart has
and and patch things sort of
strategically so that it brings you up
to date with where you want to be and
then deleting of course
goes through and using that same sort of
yaml syntax says okay remove these items
back out of the cluster i want to come
back to upgrade and delete in a moment
but one more question about templates
even though i would not as a helm user
be modifying the template there is still
the question of what does it look like
before it gets expanded if i'm looking
at the code i'm
aiming at a certain result i understand
there is a way to
preview the expanded templates before
they get pushed up to kubernetes can you
explain that
yeah part of the
so that they're kind of multi-phases as
you're rendering a template right so the
helm client will read in the chart you
know uncompress the file read the
chart.yaml and then iterate through the
template directory find all the
templates load them into memory and then
take the given values and express them
in dml at that stage right there you can
sort of interrupt it and say just you
know output the results of this and stop
that can be a very useful thing if you
want to say check your temp your
rendered yml into a github repository or
if you want to pipe the results of that
template
out into another program that has to do
some other kind of modification or
ingestion of that so it is definitely
possible to do that you have the command
helm template to be able to do that just
render the templates dump the result to
standard output as actually great for
debugging as well but
that is actually sort of like
a
developer story but not typically what
we tend to think the end users do as a
matter of course right the people who
are actually installing and upgrading
things i understand there are some
subtleties where
the preview template may not be
identical to the way it runs on the
kubernetes cluster can you explain that
sure i'll jump in here
the differences will end up being is you
can
tell helm to do things differently for
different versions of kubernetes
and so when you're interacting with the
cluster then we can detect the version
or helm can detect the version of
kubernetes you're running and then see
what logic you'll want to do for that
particular version of kubernetes
an example of this is kubernetes apis
some of those manifest those documents
we've talked about have changed over
time many times things will be uh beta
and not generally available and people
will start using them in production and
then when a generally available version
comes out you'll want to switch to that
and you've got to deal with sometimes
different versions of kubernetes
providing different versions you can
automate that when you run something
like helm template we don't have an
actual cluster you're interacting with
and so we have a default set of
configuration and we'll assume a certain
version of kubernetes usually you know
it's one of the latest released versions
the latest release version of uh helm
and we'll assume that version and so
some things might come out differently
if you're running a different version of
kubernetes that that's probably one of
the easiest examples
let's get back to upgrade and delete
starting with upgrade why would i want
to upgrade well a simple reason you
might want to upgrade is you know your
application has had a new version and
take a database we've talked about
databases say there was a patch release
version of your database that had bug
fixes or security fixes just like if i
were on linux i'd want to go upgrade my
database to pull in those fixes the same
thing happens inside of a kubernetes
cluster you want to get those new
versions right the new revision of your
actual software and so that's that's a
big reason that people upgrade i think
another one that was maybe a little
surprising to us was that people over
time decide to change their
configuration right so when you think
about the way a debian package manager
or homebrew or something like that works
you tend to install the software and
then configure it after it's installed
you don't have to upgrade for a
configuration
but in a cluster managing package
manager like kubernetes you're pushing
the configuration into these same
declarative files that hold all the
operational information and there's no
separation of concerns between
configuration and operational
information and consequently if you want
to change your the way that your helm
chart is working you will often have to
upgrade it by just merely supplying
different configuration values and then
running the upgrade command the
interesting thing about the way
kubernetes works is because it's
declarative and because
one particular parameter might get
injected into 15 or 20 different
kubernetes objects a simple what appears
to be a simple one-line change to a
configuration parameter may actually
result in
you know half a dozen or a dozen or more
different kubernetes objects being sort
of redeployed
so
our upgrading logic then had to be even
for these cases where you weren't
changing from say postgres1 to postgres
two right the
ability of the package manager to be
able to do this sort of smooth
upgrade with strategic patches just
fixing the things that are needed and
cycling the the objects that need to be
cycled and leaving everything else alone
that was all a very critical critical
thing even in these cases of simple
configuration change seemingly simple
configuration change
in these multiple object changes can
there be partial failure modes where the
upgrade
not only doesn't complete but it
modifies the system and leaves you in a
partial state
yeah one of the biggest risks in these
kinds of declarative
systems where
you would declare a bunch of things that
all work together and are tied together
in in many cases by strings that the
system interprets for you and connects
in specific ways there is a there's
always a risk that
one thing
won't quite attach to other things
correctly or
a slight configuration modification and
one thing will render it entirely
incompatible with another object there
are some things in kubernetes that are
immutable and other things that are
mutable
and there can be occasions where a
mutable thing gets changed but the
system can't change the immutable thing
so there are a number of different cases
where you can get yourself into a
situation where
some one piece has failed or a couple
pieces have failed after an upgrade
which is why helm has a rollback command
that will essentially say okay well you
know reverse back out those patches we
just applied and see if we can get
ourselves back to a stable state that
means helm has to retain a little more
state information about what your
cluster looks like but we found that to
be an invaluable tool right we of course
every every software developer ever says
oh well you know before you install this
in real life go test it out but we all
know that there are those situations
where it didn't show up in the testing
environment or you were in a rush and
forgot to test it out or something like
that so commands like rollback make it
possible to get you out of out of holes
like that when when something goes wrong
and i think it's important to also note
that these things were you're updating
kubernetes and something could go wrong
where one thing gets maybe patched and
another thing can't because it's
immutable and then you end up in a
broken state those are parts of
kubernetes not so much helm if i were
manually just working with these yaml
files and i did the same thing i could
end up in the same bad state it's one of
the reasons i like helm rollback because
if i somehow screw up i can easily roll
back
multiple configuration things all part
of that same chart kubernetes itself has
a rollback capability this helm rollback
built on top of kubernetes rollback helm
is not built on kubernetes rollback it's
built on kubernetes patch system and
basically
we reverse out the last patch that we
did by
recalculating the patch to go back to
its previous state as as one of my
friends bridget who's one of the leads
in the home community likes to say you
know there's no time machine included
here
the
process of rolling back is essentially
saying hey we uh we generated a diff of
this yaml and and that resulted in this
yemel and then we uploaded it and that
resulted in a broken state so we're
going to reverse the diff generate a new
yaml that resets it back to the way it
used to be and and and run that so it is
essentially an automated version of what
you would do if you were manually
repairing and said okay so what did i
change i changed these nine things so
i've got to reverse all of these back
out again it reminds me a little bit of
if i go to undo a commit on github if i
go to undo a commit on github it just
doesn't take out my top commit it
creates a new commit that undid what the
previous one did and so it's a little
bit of trying to do that exact same kind
of thing the other topic that i
said i'd get back to is delete what does
that do the helm delete function
essentially because helm knows which
objects have been placed in the
kubernetes cluster the helm delete
function will go in there and take all
of those and remove them
you know essentially run the the
equivalent of a coupe ctl delete command
on each thing that it knows is
associated with the chart there's there
are some fascinating nuances with the
way kubernetes works it makes delete a
very dangerous operation in some cases
and helm has gone to considerable
lengths to avoid some of these because
kubernetes has
the the concept of ownership where a
deployment will spin up a replica set
that it then claims to own and a replica
set will spin up pods which it then
claims to own
and the desirable impact is when you
delete the deployment you want it to
delete the replica set and have the
replica set delete all of the pods and
so helm doesn't need to track where the
replica sets are and what individual
pods are running it just needs to track
the deployment there are other cases
that are iffy like crds you might you
might create a crd inside of your
cluster but when you delete a crd you
don't necessarily want to delete every
single instance of the crd in fact in
many cases you don't actually want to
delete a crd at all and so we put a
number of safeguards in to prevent some
of these edge cases from happening but
for the most part
helm will track the top level objects
that are created and then allow we'll
trust that kubernetes parent child
relationship will take care of cleaning
up all the children that were created by
the parent objects we've been talking
for the first part of the interview
about more or less what it does going in
to detail i want to
change directions now a bit and talk
about
what kind of
public repositories are available
containing
open source charts
wow there are a lot of repositories
containing open source charts originally
when helm2 came out they created a
charts repository and it was example
charts
and people started adding more and more
and it turned from example charts that
to
hundreds and hundreds of charts put
together by people at different
companies and the growth became mostly
unmanageable and so we shifted hal marty
had this ability to handle many
different repositories and so we kind of
shifted from having a central repository
that everybody was using to many
repositories and we found that people at
companies all over or just individuals
would get together on their own just
create these open source charts and you
can search for those now in on artifact
hub but there are there's some from
companies like bitnami which is now part
of vmware which has a set of really
excellent charts i installed something
just over this past weekend and it
needed mariadb and it got it from the
bitnami set because it's really robust
and they keep it up to date and there's
just so many most of the major companies
that i found many of them you know
microsoft included and amazon they'll
have charts out there that are public to
install software
and
all of this is all in open source in
fact i'm not familiar with people doing
widely distributed proprietary charts
they're making all of these things where
they want people to consume and run
their software open source as far as the
charts go and so there are thousands and
thousands of
charts for different pieces of software
and i do think it's right to look at
artifact hub as sort of like the first
place you go to find charts uh it is
sort of like the docker hub or the npm
of the helm world uh also has all kinds
of other artifacts that are not just
helm charts it's a great place to kind
of see what cloud native packages are
out there and available for install and
what systems are supported matt farina
of course is one of the
architects and and lead developers on
that project but it's just uh since
artifact hub came around it's been so
much easier to find and install
not just helm charts but a wide variety
of different kubernetes and cloud native
technologies if i picked some popular
open source software you mentioned
mariadb matt farina and i did a search
on rf type would i be likely to get
multiple
search results that reflect different
opinions by
practitioners of the best way to install
that piece of software
yes you very much would
and that becomes one of the decision
points because when you're creating a
chart there's more than one way to do
things
what how do you craft the user
experience what are the
default parameters right what are the
default values for the parameters what
are those things and people developers
you know we know they have different
opinions look at all the javascript
frameworks people have created and the
same thing for packaging up the
applications to run they'll go ahead and
have different opinions on how you
should do that and they'll distribute
them separately artifact hub allows you
to list all of those but they do
have ways of saying okay is this you
know
chart from the same people who published
the application themselves so if mariadb
themselves created their own chart it
would be flagged as the official one
from them there's also things like
verified repositories you can verify
that the person who owns the repository
listed it here for that end to end
verification they'll show off other
characteristics such as the container
images are there known vulnerabilities
in those and so because you have all of
these you know different ways people
could package them up you can't just say
there's one i'm going to install it you
want to be able to easily evaluate those
and the artifact hub tries to
bubble up those details to make it easy
to figure out what those are so you can
make the decision that's right for you
if you are a software vendor
now and you want people to use
your software to try it out is it
becoming almost a standard that you have
to issue a helm chart along with your
software to make it simple for people to
try it out you know i would say that it
has become sort of a standard there are
devops people who like to work with
their own raw yaml files uh just to give
an example here and they would prefer to
do that because they know kubernetes
they know their applications really well
but when they want to distribute it
widely they still end up needing to
create a helm chart just to help them
get the distribution of their core
software and so i think for some time if
you want to get something out there and
easily consumed you end up offering a
helm chart as an option to install it
and many people use that within a large
enterprise
if it's large enough you will have
some software that is used in multiple
places throughout the enterprise
or you have groups building something
that another group needs
can an enterprise set up an internal
repo for sharing helm charts within
their boundaries
yeah it is very easy to set up a helm
repository and
the reason we made it such was so that
both enterprises and you know
individuals and everything in between
would be able to easily set up
repositories the way they wanted so we
even had published
instructions uh that say hey you want to
set one up internally using these tools
here's how to do it you want to set it
up publicly on using nothing but github
here's how to do it and and try and sort
of stay on top of
all the different ways that people could
stand up a simple helm repository for
you know again anything from the weekend
project to
the corporate helm charts that have
already passed the internal security
reviews and things like that matt farina
and i have both worked at a number of
places together and one of the virtues
of that is when we worked at hp we
understood what it meant to need a
strong secured internal only repository
when we worked at uh
you know palantir.net doing websites we
understood the need to be able to
publish something very simply and very
quickly out on a website where other
people could make use of it and and
we've kind of learned this lesson and
tried to apply it as have the rest of
the helm core maintainers you know to
make it as simple as possible to stand
up home repositories that meet the needs
of you and your organization
we're getting close to end of time matt
butcher is there anything you would
really like the listeners to know that
we haven't talked about before we wrap
up yeah i think that for me
the the joy of working on a project like
helm has been to see it sort of flourish
over the years uh to have an increasing
number of people join the community with
different needs and
work their way through those first hello
world examples to the point where
they're producing their own charts
now as we enter this kind of what i
think of as like the third phase of
helm's life right where helm is sort of
present in every kubernetes ecosystem
it becomes more and more important for
us to kind of find the leaders in the
community who are going to become
you know the the ones who lead others in
the future into helm and the ones who
make the decisions of what's going to go
into home 4 and helm five and home six
so if that's the kind of thing that uh
that resonates with you you know we've
got an open public developer meeting
every thursday details on that are on
the helm community website you know we
have roles available for people who want
to help triage issues and and work their
way into becoming core maintainers we're
really excited as we get looking in the
years beyond to what's going to come in
as features for the helm4 project once
we get going on that matt farina would
you like to get anything
covered that we missed so far
you know uh in addition to what uh matt
butcher said i think i'm amazed at how
many supporting tools there are for helm
now
right there there's helm itself you know
the package manager but whether you want
to create charts or put them in through
ci and testing and linting or just as i
learned this morning somebody sent me a
whole new package to help you work with
charts that i'd never seen before
the ecosystem of people on their own or
at companies and just all around have
created so many tools to help support
people who want to work with helm and
charts that almost anything i'm like ah
i want to go create this thing it's a
neat idea i jump into a search engine
and look for it and i found somebody
already has because there are so many
people using it and trying to make
themselves and others successful with
what they're doing that there's just so
many tools and methodologies out there
matt but you're where can people find
you
yeah the easiest places for for people
to find me on twitter i'm technosofos
pretty much everywhere i'm technosofas
i hang out pretty regularly and the
kubernetes slack the cncf slack as ceo
of fermion you'll see me blogging fairly
common fairly frequently at fermion.com
looking forward to seeing people in
person in valencia spain at kubecon
mafrina where can people find you
usually i have a very boring username
everywhere it's matt farina whether
you're on github or twitter or in cncf
or kubernetes slack if you want to find
me and all the other places if you go to
mattforina.com i think i've got links
off to most of the other places that
you'll find me where can listeners find
your book
the helm book was published by o'reilly
so it's easy to get the book anywhere
that carries o'reilly books including
you know the the big ones like amazon
and barnes and noble and things like
that i believe it's also available as an
e-book directly from o'reilly's website
and and it's also available i think
through their safari subscriptions
great matt butcher and matt farina thank
you very much for speaking to software
engineering radio thanks for having us
yeah thanks for having us for software
engineering radio this has been robert
blumen thank you for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at essie radio dot
dot
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening